<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>Reia Reference Guide</title>
        <author>
            <orgname>Walton Hoops</orgname>
            <email>me@waltonhoops.com</email>
        </author>
    </info>
    <part>
        <title>Programming with Reia</title>
        <chapter>
            <title>Getting Started</title>
            <sect1>
                <title>What You Need Before Getting Started</title>
                <para>As of this writing, this text only describes installing and using Reia under
                    Linux.  It is assumed that you already know how to find and install software on
                    your choosen Linux distribution both through your distributions package manager
                    and from source.  It is also assumed that you are somewhat confortable with
                    tools such as Git and Rake and will be able to do some basic troubleshooting if
                    things don't work quite as expected.  If any of this does not describe you, you
                    should probably expect to have a harder time following along.</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Installation</title>
                <para>As it is still in the early stages of development, installing Reia is not
                    quite as smooth as many more mature languages which can be installed directly
                    from your package manager. In order to install Reia you are first going to need
                    to compile it from source. To do that, your going to need a few basic components:<itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Erlang R12B-3 or greater</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Ruby 1.8.7 or greater with Rake</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Git</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist> First, we'll need to checkout the <link
                        xlink:href="https://github.com/tarcieri/reia">GitHub repository</link>. To
                    do so run:
                    <screen><command>git clone https://github.com/tarcieri/reia.git</command></screen>your
                    output should look something
                    like:<programlisting>Cloning into reia...
remote: Counting objects: 8727, done.
remote: Compressing objects: 100% (3343/3343), done.
remote: Total 8727 (delta 5380), reused 8590 (delta 5296)
Receiving objects: 100% (8727/8727), 7.25 MiB | 759 KiB/s, done.
Resolving deltas: 100% (5380/5380), done.</programlisting>Great!
                    Now change to the newly created directory. It should look something like:
                    <programlisting><textobject><textdata fileref="listings/reia-dir.txt"/></textobject></programlisting>If
                    all is well you should now be able to build Reia itself. To do so simply
                    run:<screen><command>rake</command></screen>This both builds Reia and runs the
                    test suite. A successful build will look like
                    so:<programlisting><textobject><textdata fileref="listings/reia-build.txt"/></textobject></programlisting>If
                    there are errors reported during the build you will probaby want to ask around
                    on the Reia Google Group to find out what the problem is.</para>
                <para>Now you have two choices. You can either do a <link linkend="system_install"
                        >system-wide installation</link>, or a <link linkend="local_install">local
                    installation</link>.</para>
                <sect2 xml:id="system_install"><title>System Install: The Easy Way</title><para>To do a regular system-wide install of Reia, you need to run the following (replacing sudo
                        with whatever command your system uses to become root):
                        <screen><command>sudo rake install</command></screen>Note that this will
                        probably not work if you are using RVM. If you are using RVM, ensure that
                        you have installed Ruby and Rake through your package manager, and run
                        <screen><command>rvm use --system</command></screen>before attempting to run
                        rake install. If everything goes well you should see the following::
                        <programlisting><textobject><textdata fileref="listings/reia-system-install.txt"/></textobject></programlisting>Excellent!
                    Now your ready to start coding with Reia! Procede to <link linkend="ch2">Chapter 2</link></para>
                </sect2><sect2 xml:id="local_install">
                    <title>Local Install: The Hard Way</title>
                    <para>Doing a local installation of Reia is quite a bit more complex, but has
                        the benifit of not requiring root priviledges, working well with RVM, and
                        being somewhat simpler to manage. The first thing you'll need to do is make
                        a directory inside your home directory to install Reia into. For our
                        purposes lets use ~/.reia. First we need to make the directories where Reia
                        should install
                        itself:<screen><command>mkdir -p ~/.reia/bin</command>
<command>mkdir -p ~/.reia/lib</command></screen>Then
                        we need to set up our enviorment variables that tell Reia where to install
                        itself:<screen><command>export REIA_BIN_DIR=~/.reia/bin # This is where Reia will place it's executables</command>
<command>export ERL_LIB_DIR=~/.reia/lib # This is where Reia will place it's system libraries</command></screen>and
                        finally you are ready to install.
                        Run<screen><command>rake install</command></screen> and you should see
                        something
                        like:<programlisting><textobject><textdata fileref="listings/reia-local-install.txt"/></textobject></programlisting>Phew!
                        Almost done! Last but not least you need to make some changes to you
                        ~/.bashrc (if you're not using bash, you will need to modify these
                        instructions for your shell). Add the following lines to your ~/.bashrc
                        file:<programlisting>export PATH="$PATH:~/.reia/bin" # Adds the bin directory to your path
export ERL_LIBS="/home/walton/.reia/lib/reia/" # Additional directory where the Erlang will look for libraries
export REIA_HOME="/home/walton/.reia/lib/reia/" # Where Reia should look for it's core libraries</programlisting>Last but not least you need either start a new shell, or run <screen><command>source ~/.bashrc</command></screen> to pull your changes into the shell.
                        There! If you've done everything correctly you should now be ready to move
                        onto <link linkend="ch2">Chapter 2</link></para>
                </sect2></sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter xml:id="ch2">
            <title>The Basics</title>
            <para>Well, the first thing to learn about Reia is IRE. For those of you who have used
                Ruby or Python this should be very familiar teritorry, it's a simple REPL
                (Read-Eval-Print-Loop) like IRB or the Python shell. For those of you who haven't
                IRE is a shell where you can input a command of Reia code, and see the results
                printed on the screen.  For example lets try the traditional Hello World program.
                First run: <screen><command>ire</command></screen> to start the shell.  You should see something like:</para>
        </chapter>
    </part>
</book>
