<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>Reia Reference Guide</title>
        <author>
            <orgname>Walton Hoops</orgname>
            <email>me@waltonhoops.com</email>
        </author>
    </info>
    <part>
        <title>Reference</title>
        <chapter>
            <title>Getting Started</title>
            <sect1>
                <title>What You Need Before Getting Started</title>
                <para>As of this writing, this text only describes installing and using Reia under
                    Linux.  It is assumed that you already know how to find and install software on
                    your choosen Linux distribution both through your distributions package manager
                    and from source.  It is also assumed that you are somewhat confortable with
                    tools such as Git and Rake and will be able to do some basic troubleshooting if
                    things don't work quite as expected.  If any of this does not describe you, you
                    should probably expect to have a harder time following along.</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Installation</title>
                <para>As it is still in the early stages of development, installing Reia is not
                    quite as smooth as many more mature languages which can be installed directly
                    from your package manager. In order to install Reia you are first going to need
                    to compile it from source. To do that, your going to need a few basic components:<itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Erlang R12B-3 or greater</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Ruby 1.8.7 or greater with Rake</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Git</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist> First, we'll need to checkout the <link
                        xlink:href="https://github.com/tarcieri/reia">GitHub repository</link>. To
                    do so run:
                    <screen><command>git clone https://github.com/tarcieri/reia.git</command></screen>your
                    output should look something
                    like:<programlisting>Cloning into reia...
remote: Counting objects: 8727, done.
remote: Compressing objects: 100% (3343/3343), done.
remote: Total 8727 (delta 5380), reused 8590 (delta 5296)
Receiving objects: 100% (8727/8727), 7.25 MiB | 759 KiB/s, done.
Resolving deltas: 100% (5380/5380), done.</programlisting>Great!
                    Now change to the newly created directory. It should look something like:
                    <programlisting><textobject><textdata fileref="listings/reia-dir.txt"/></textobject></programlisting>If
                    all is well you should now be able to build Reia itself. To do so simply
                    run:<screen><command>rake</command></screen>This both builds Reia and runs the
                    test suite. A successful build will look like
                    so:<programlisting><textobject><textdata fileref="listings/reia-build.txt"/></textobject></programlisting>If
                    there are errors reported during the build you will probaby want to ask around
                    on the Reia Google Group to find out what the problem is. Lastly, in order to
                    install Reia onto your system you need to run:
                    <screen><command>sudo rake install</command></screen>Which produces the
                    following:
                    <programlisting><textobject><textdata fileref="listings/reia-install.txt"/></textobject></programlisting>Excellent!
                    Now your ready to start coding with Reia!</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
    </part>
</book>
